"The Negative Effects of
Cold Plunges for Building Muscle"
In my last video,
I talked about how
the benefits of cold plunges
appear to be due
to the placebo effect.
But cold-water immersion
isn’t just futile
but may be a foe when it comes
to our muscle mass.
A key take-home message is
that if the goal of training
is to build muscle mass
and strength,
regular cold plunges after
exercise may not be beneficial.
It all started
with this study in 2006,
showing that cold-water
immersion of muscles
may actually interfere
with regenerative processes
and retard rather than support
the desired improvements
of muscular performance.
Since then, independent
corroborating evidence
has continued to accumulate
that post-exercise cooling
diminishes muscle adaptations
to strength training,
leading to punny
click-bait titles like
"Cryotherapy: Are we freezing
the benefits of exercise?",
"Is the ice bath
finally melting?",
"The cold truth," "Cooling down
the use of cryotherapy."
Here’s a typical study showing
that cold plunges
substantially attenuate
long-term gains
in muscle mass and strength.
Twelve weeks
of strength training
with just typical
active recovery
led to a significant increase
in muscle mass in the quads,
but the same amount of training
with cold plunges
barely moved the needle.
And this manifested in
significantly less strength,
whether we’re talking
maximum leg-press strength,
knee extension,
isometric torque,
or rate of force development.
Note that smaller muscles
don’t necessarily lead
to less strength.
In this study,
the blunted muscle fiber growth
didn’t translate to
impaired strength development,
but post-exercise cold plunges
should be avoided
if you do actually want
bigger muscles.
But there are folks,
like long-distance runners,
who may not want
that extra bulk;
so, cold plunges may be a way
to keep their muscles smaller.
This is probably
the most rigorous study
involving measuring muscle mass
using the gold standard,
MRI imaging,
and actually taking muscle
biopsies before and after.
And, while both groups gained
muscle mass and strength
following training,
these gains were
significantly smaller
in the cold-water
immersion group,
compared with
the active recovery group.
And the cross-sectional area
of fast-twitch muscle fibers
also increased
only in the control group.
There have been all sorts
of published points
and counterpoints
about the cold-water dampening
effect on hypertrophy gains.
Here’s a systematic review
with meta-analysis
of all such studies.
A harmful effect of cold-water
immersion was verified
for every single
strength parameter measure:
one-rep maximum,
maximal isometric strength,
strength endurance,
and ballistic efforts
all reduced by cold plunges.
So, it appears useless
for endurance training
and deleterious
for strength training.
Why are people still doing it?
Here’s a 2024 meta-analysis,
and the title says it all:
Throwing cold water
on muscle growth.
This may be because
cold-water immersion
puts the chill
on muscle protein synthesis,
both in the hours immediately
following exercise
and during weeks
of strength training.
Another explanation
for cold-induced
reductions in strength
is that cold-water immersion
constricts the arteries
and causes a reduction
in blood flow
which is important for muscle
strength and development.
A 50 percent drop
in femoral blood flow,
compared to warmer water
or control.
Reductions in muscle blood flow
reduces the oxygen supply,
which plays a role in
the decreased muscle mass, too.
Cold plunges also blunt
the testosterone response.
So, the impaired testosterone
response may be another reason
for the attenuated strength
and muscle growth.
So, cold plunges following
resistance exercise sessions
should be discouraged,
but they are said not to impair
aerobic training.
That’s not always the case,
though,
as some studies show a reduction
in aerobic fitness as well.
This study found that muscle
warming was better than cooling,
thought due to the slowing
of glycogen resynthesis
in the cold.
Mean power output was
better preserved hours after
an all-out arm-cycling exercise.
The cold did worse than control,
and after the muscle heating,
there was hardly any decrease
in power output at all.
So, wait, should we instead
be taking a warm bath or sauna
after exercise
instead of an ice-water bath?
Regardless,
cryotherapy is apparently
not as cool as it seems.